[Music]
in 1969 a correlation analysis performed
by dr greger no relation and he spelled
it wrong
found this rather tight correlation
between animal protein intake in
countries and intestinal cancer
mortality
in the 70s this relationship was
extended to breast cancer too and animal
fat implicated as well
but it all kind of
travels together in the same foods along
with dietary cholesterol and there's a
significant correlation between high
consumption of cholesterol-containing
food items and the worldwide
distribution of colon cancer as well a
large and highly significant correlation
even after controlling for other dietary
factors such as animal fat and fiber
supporting the possibility of a cause
and effect relationship between
cholesterol intake and colon cancer so
is dietary cholesterol co-carcinogenic
for human colon cancer let's find out by
feeding some to rats
inject rats with a carcinogen and
cholesterol eating rats get tumors in
half the time and all die off whereas
most the cholesterol-free group survives
but the relevance of animal data to the
human situation is debatable
how would the cholesterol in cancer link
even work
well
we don't need to consume
any cholesterol since our body makes all
that it needs and when we do consume
extra there's a limit to the amount of
cholesterol the body can absorb so where
does the excess go down to our colon and
so the cells lining our colon where
colon cancer rises are therefore
constantly exposed to fecal cholesterol
should a cancerous or pre-cancerous
polyp arise
maybe all that extra cholesterol would
help it grow faster the amount of
cholesterol we eat could thus be a
factor determining the rate of
development growth or spread of such a
tumor
this was all just kind of speculation
back in the 70s but they realized that
if it were true i mean that would be
good news since a low cholesterol diet
cutting down on meat dairy eggs and junk
the only foods that really have
cholesterol
would be a feasible cheap safe way to
help prevent and treat colon cancer so
what's the 40-year update
country by country correlation can never
do more than just inspire studies like
this the largest nationwide
population-based case control study to
date to assess the association between
cholesterol intake and several types of
cancer and
they found
dietary cholesterol intake was
associated with increased risk of
cancers of the stomach colon rectum
pancreas lung breast
kidney bladder and bone marrow
non-hodgkin's lymphoma so the flip side
is that a diet low in cholesterol may
play a role in the prevention of several
cancers
what does that mean food wise cutting
down on meat dairy and eggs which may
increase risk of cancer though eating
diaries would probably just increase
risk of paper cuts
lots of fiber though
the findings of this study should
essentially be viewed as an indication
that diets rich in meat dairy products
and eggs
is an unfavorable indicator of the risk
of several common cancers
two cancers they didn't look into though
were endometrial cancer and throat
cancer
put all the studies on cholesterol
consumption the risk of endometrial
cancer together cancer of the lining of
the uterus they found a dose response
meaning more cholesterol consumption
associated with more cancer six percent
for every 100 milligrams extra a day so
like a daily omelet might increase
cancer risk by about 20 percent
maybe because the extra cholesterol is
converted into estrogen or it may just
be the increased oxidative stress
reflected in higher levels of oxidized
cholesterol
i talk about that in my alzheimer's
series
there also appears to be a dose response
relationship with pancreatic cancer one
of our most dismal malignancies
the compilation of studies found the
risk increased by eight percent for
every 100 milligrams of cholesterol so
that would be like 30 higher risk of
pancreatic cancer for a daily omelet
and finally
throat cancer
increased risk was observed for elevated
cholesterol intake about 85 percent
higher odds consistent with the other
studies
yeah maybe it's the oxidation but maybe
it's the inflammation however we can't
be sure it's the cholesterol itself
that's the blame elevated cholesterol
intake
could just be a stand-in indicator that
a diet rich in meat eggs and dairy
products may have unfavorable effects
[Music]
uh